<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>API on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/api/</link>
    <description>Recent content in API on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/api/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Downloading occurrences from a long list of species</title>
      <link>/post/downloading-long-species-lists-on-gbif/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/downloading-long-species-lists-on-gbif/</guid>
      <description>It is now possible to download up to 100,000 names on GBIF!
Until recently it was not possible to download occurrences for more than a few hundred species at the same time, but is now possible to request more species names (up to 100,000 taxonkeys).
For those multiple taxa downloaders out there, GBIF now supports download requests of up to 100,000(!) taxa. That should cover most use cases :) For such large requests, however, you will need to POST you query to the Occurrence Download API service: https://t.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not a bird download</title>
      <link>/post/not-a-bird/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/not-a-bird/</guid>
      <description>Recently we were asked on GitHub whether there was a way to get all animal occurrences that are not a bird. This seems like an easy enough request, but unfortunately, there is currently no way to exclude groups from a download search and get everything but a certain group.
A user can get all birds, but they can’t get no birds!
I thought this was an interesting question and probably useful for other people wanting smaller downloads, since there are currenly around half a billion occurrence records for birds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big National Checklists</title>
      <link>/post/big-national-checklists/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/big-national-checklists/</guid>
      <description>link to interactive map
Big 15-300K total namesMedium 5-15K total namesSmall 0-5K total namesHere I plot the total names in checklists published on GBIF linked to a single country. A checklist dataset is a term for any dataset that contains primarily a list of taxonomic names. National species checklists are lists of species recorded from a country usually through some organized effort. GBIF has published a guide on best practices for making national checklist datasets, which advises making national checklists as big as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding citizen science datasets on GBIF</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-citizen-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-citizen-science/</guid>
      <description>Can we automatically label citizen science datasets? The short answer is yes, partially.
Why label GBIF datasets as &amp;ldquo;citizen science&amp;rdquo;? What is citizen science? Citizen science is scientific research conducted, in whole or in part, by amateur (or non-professional) scientists. Citizen science is sometimes described as &amp;ldquo;public participation in scientific research,&amp;rdquo; participatory monitoring, and participatory action research (wikipedia definition).
Citizen science on GBIF A 2016 study showed that nearly half of all occurrence records shared through the GBIF network come from datasets with significant volunteer contributions (for more information, see our &amp;ldquo;citizen science&amp;rdquo; page on gbif.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>