<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 21:38:52 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 21:38:52 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>What is it? A place for GBIF staff and guest bloggers to contribute:
 Statistics Graphs Tutorials Ideas Opinions  Who can contribute? If you would like to contribute you can contact jwaller@gbif.org. Guest blogs are very welcome.
How can I write a post? There is a short turtorial on the blog github.
What about the developer blog? Currently the developer blog no longer being updated but an archive will be maintained.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will citizen science take over?</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-citizen-science-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-citizen-science-data/</guid>
      <description>What is citizen scienceCitizen science is scientific research conducted, in whole or in part, by amateur (or non-professional) scientists. Biodiversity observations by citizen scientists have become significant in the last 10 years thanks to projects like:
eBirdiNaturalistArtportalen SwedenArtsdatabanken NorwaySouthern African Bird AtlasBird Life AustrailiaDansk Ornitoligisk ForeningGreat Back Yard Bird CountThe rise of citizen science on the GBIF networkCitizen scientists have been contributing a large and growing percentage of records to the GBIF network.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using shapefiles on GBIF data with R</title>
      <link>/post/shapefiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/shapefiles/</guid>
      <description>Not all filters are born equal It happens sometimes that users need GBIF data that fall within specific boundaries. The GBIF Portal provides a location filter where it is possible to draw a rectangle or a polygon on the map and get the occurrence records within this shape. However these tools have a limited precision and occasionally the job calls for more complex shapes than the GBIF Portal currently supports.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharing images, sounds and videos on GBIF</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-multimedia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-multimedia/</guid>
      <description>This blog post covers the publication of multimedia on GBIF. However, it is not intended to be documentation. For more information, please check the references below.
NB: GBIF does not host original multimedia files and there is no way to upload pictures to the platform. For more information, please read the how to publish paragraphs.
Media displayed on the GBIF portal Let&amp;rsquo;s say that you are looking for pictures of otters, or perhaps the call of a sea eagle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding citizen science datasets on GBIF</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-citizen-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-citizen-science/</guid>
      <description>Can we automatically label citizen science datasets? The short answer is yes, partially.
Why label GBIF datasets as &amp;ldquo;citizen science&amp;rdquo;? What is citizen science? Citizen science is scientific research conducted, in whole or in part, by amateur (or non-professional) scientists. Citizen science is sometimes described as &amp;ldquo;public participation in scientific research,&amp;rdquo; participatory monitoring, and participatory action research (wikipedia definition).
Citizen science on GBIF A 2016 study showed that nearly half of all occurrence records shared through the GBIF network come from datasets with significant volunteer contributions (for more information, see our &amp;ldquo;citizen science&amp;rdquo; page on gbif.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plot almost anything using the GBIF maps API</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-maps-api-using-r-and-leaflet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-maps-api-using-r-and-leaflet/</guid>
      <description>The GBIF maps API is an under-used but powerful web service provided by GBIF. The maps API is used by the main GBIF portal to create the maps including the big map used on gbif.org. We can make a simple call to the API by pasting the link below into a web browser.
https://api.gbif.org/v2/map/occurrence/density/0/0/0@1x.png?style=purpleYellow.pointYou should end up with an image like this.This api call is composed essentially of two elements</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding gridded datasets</title>
      <link>/post/finding-gridded-datasets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/finding-gridded-datasets/</guid>
      <description>EBCC Atlas of European Breeding Birds (gridded)Naturalis Biodiversity Center (NL) - Aves (not gridded)Gridded data in GBIFGridded datasets are a known problem at GBIF. Many datasets have equally-spaced points in a regular pattern. These datasets are usually systematic national surveys or data taken from some atlas (“so-called rasterized collection designs”).
In this blog post I will describe how I found gridded dataset in GBIF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GBIF download trends</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-download-trends/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-download-trends/</guid>
      <description>Link To App
Explanation of toolThis tool plots the downloads through time for species or other taxonomic groups with more than 25 downloads at GBIF. Downloads at GBIF most often occur through the web interface. In a previous post, we saw that most users are downloading data from GBIF via filtering by scientific name (aka Taxon Key). Since the GBIF index currently sits at over 1 billion records (a 400+GB CSV), most users will simplying filter by their taxonomic group of interest and then generate a download.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GBIF data quality issues and flags what do they mean?</title>
      <link>/post/issues-and-flags/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2000 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/issues-and-flags/</guid>
      <description>GBIF gets records from around 1600 (and counting) occurrence datasets.Not all of the data-providers have the time or resources to make sure their datasets are free from errors.
As a service to the biodiversity user community, GBIF flags records that might contain an obvious issue. Some flags are not easy to understand, and most users are probably not aware that they exist or filter them all out by default by leaving the “include records where coordinates are flagged as suspcious” unchecked.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>