<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DOI on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/doi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in DOI on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/doi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Did you know that...? - some of the lesser known functionalities around GBIF.org</title>
      <link>/post/did-you-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/did-you-know/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the first-ever virtual GBIF 2021 Global Nodes Meeting, GBIFS hosted a &amp;ldquo;game show&amp;rdquo;: a one-hour &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gnm2021.gbif.org/sessions/friday-nodes-vs-helpdesk&#34;&gt;battle of Nodes vs. helpdesk&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. The not-so-hidden goal was to demonstrate some of the lesser known functionalities of GBIF.org through a fun, interactive session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&#34;vimeo-player&#34; src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/571521342&#34; width=100% height=&#34;300&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a summary of the questions and answers from this session, plus some extras that did not manage to make it into the time frame of the event. The summary is following the layout and sequence of the interactive hour:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Derived datasets</title>
      <link>/post/derived-datasets/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/derived-datasets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve finished an analysis using GBIF-mediated data, you&amp;rsquo;re writing up your manuscript and checking all the references, but you&amp;rsquo;re unsure of how to cite GBIF. If you &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=how+to+cite+GBIF&#34;&gt;Google it&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably end up reading our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gbif.org/citation-guidelines&#34;&gt;citation guideslines&lt;/a&gt; and quickly realize that GBIF is all about DOIs. Datasets have their own DOIs and downloads of aggregated data also have their own DOIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe you didn&amp;rsquo;t download data through the GBIF.org portal. Maybe you relied on an R package like rgbif or dismo that retrived data synchronously from the GBIF API? Maybe a grad student downloaded if for you? Maybe you accessed and analyzed the data using a cloud computing service, like Microsoft Azure or Amazon Web Services? In any case, which DOI do you cite &lt;em&gt;if you don&amp;rsquo;t have one&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>