<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rgbif on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/rgbif/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rgbif on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/rgbif/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with names in rgbif</title>
      <link>/post/rgbif-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rgbif-names/</guid>
      <description>Matching names to the GBIF backbone is one of the most important steps in any GBIF workflow.
There are several functions within rgbif that deal with scientific names, so it can be difficult to know what function to use when trying to match names to the GBIF backbone.
There are several names
name_backbone()name_usage()name_suggest()name_lookup()If you just want to match your names to the GBIF backbone (get taxonkeys), I would use rgbif::name_backbone().</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with scientific names in rgbif</title>
      <link>/post/rgbif-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rgbif-names/</guid>
      <description>When starting to work with rgbif and GBIF it is sometimes hard to know where to start.
In this guide I will be going through.
In my opinion there are around 5 steps to any GBIF-realted research project.
match your names to the GBIF backbonedownload your GBIF subsetclean your downloadrun your modelcite your downloadAll of these steps can be done in rgbif.
Match names to the GBIF backboneThis is often the most difficult task when starting to work in GBIF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Search, download, analyze and cite (repeat if necessary)</title>
      <link>/post/search-download-analyze-cite/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/search-download-analyze-cite/</guid>
      <description>Finding and accessing data There is a lot of GBIF-mediated data available. More than 1.3 B occurrence records covering hundreds of thousands of species in all part of the worlds. All free, open and available at the touch of a button. Users can download data through the GBIF.org portal, via the GBIF API, or one of the third-party tools available for programmatic access, e.g. rgbif.
If there is one area in which GBIF has been immensely successful, it&amp;rsquo;s making the data available to users.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>