<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Guest Post on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/guest-post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Guest Post on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/guest-post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>100 GBIF datasets, improved</title>
      <link>/post/100-gbif-datasets-improved/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/100-gbif-datasets-improved/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biodiversity data papers are a special kind of scientific publication. As explained by &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-12-S15-S2&#34;&gt;Chavan and Penev (2011)&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A data paper is a journal publication whose primary purpose is to describe data, rather than to report a research investigation. As such, it contains facts about data, not hypotheses and arguments in support of those hypotheses based on data, as found in a conventional research article. Its purposes are threefold: to provide a citable journal publication that brings scholarly credit to data publishers; to describe the data in a structured human-readable form; and to bring the existence of the data to the attention of the scholarly community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years many publishers of GBIF data have also published data papers describing their GBIF datasets. If the data paper manuscript was submitted to a Pensoft journal, the dataset was carefully audited (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.3.35019&#34;&gt;Penev et al. 2019&lt;/a&gt;). Manuscripts were not passed to reviewers until dataset errors in structure, format or compliance with Darwin Core recommendations were corrected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Biodiversity Informatics 💘 Wikidata?</title>
      <link>/post/wikidata/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/wikidata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Open online APIs are fantastic! You can use someone else&amp;rsquo;s infrastructure to create workflows, do research and create products without giving anything in return, except acknowledgement. But wait a minute! Why is everyone not using them? Why do we create our own data sources and suck up the costs in time and money? Not to mention the duplication of effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frictionless Data and Darwin Core</title>
      <link>/post/frictionless-data-and-darwin-core/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/frictionless-data-and-darwin-core/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frictionless data&lt;/strong&gt; is about removing the friction in working with data through the creation of tools, standards, and best practices for publishing data using the Data Package standard, a containerization format for any kind of data. It offers specifications and software around data publication, transport and consumption. Similarly to Darwin Core, data resources are presented in CSV files while the data model is described in a JSON structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>