<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Checklist on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/checklist/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Checklist on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/checklist/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to choose a dataset class on GBIF?</title>
      <link>/post/choose-dataset-type/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/choose-dataset-type/</guid>
      <description>If you are a (first time) publisher on GBIF and you are trying to decide which type of dataset would best fit your data, this blogpost is for you.
All the records shared on GBIF are organized into datasets. Each dataset is associated with some metadata describing its content (the classic &amp;ldquo;what, where, when, why, how&amp;rdquo;). The dataset&amp;rsquo;s content depends strongly on the dataset&amp;rsquo;s class. GBIF currently support four types of dataset:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Six questions answered about the GBIF Backbone Taxomomy</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-backbone-taxonomy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-backbone-taxonomy/</guid>
      <description>This past week our informatics team has been updating the Backbone taxonomy on GBIF.org. This is a fairly disruptive process which sometimes involves massive taxonomic changes but DON’T PANIC.
This update is a good thing. It means that some of the taxonomic issues reported have been addressed (see for example this issue concerning the Xylophagidae family) and that new species are now visible on GBIF. Plus, it gives me an excellent opportunity to talk about the GBIF backbone taxonomy and answer some of the questions you might have.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>