<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data quality on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/data-quality/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data quality on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/data-quality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gridded Datasets Update</title>
      <link>/post/gridded-datasets-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gridded-datasets-update/</guid>
      <description>Gridded datasets are now flagged on the GBIF registryThis update builds on work from a previous blog post.
Gridded datasets are broadly datasets that have low coordinate precision due to rasterized sampling or rounding. This can be a data quality issue because a user might assume an occurrence record has more precision than it actually does.
Current statistics572 datasets are currently flagged as gridded or rasterized on the registry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Country Centroids</title>
      <link>/post/country-centroids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/country-centroids/</guid>
      <description>Country Centroids are a known data quality issue within the GBIF network.
Sometimes data publishers will not know the exact lat-lon location of a record and will enter the lat-long center of the country instead. This is a data issue because users might be unaware that an observation is pinned to a country center and assume it is a precise location.
Below I plot the top country centroids found on GBIF within at least 1km.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunger mapping</title>
      <link>/post/hunger-mapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hunger-mapping/</guid>
      <description>Where are we missing biodiversity data?A hunger map is a map of missing biodiversity data (a biodiversity data gap). The main challenge with hunger mapping is proving that a species does not exist but should exist in a region. Hunger maps are important because they could be used to prioritize funding and digitization efforts. Currently, GBIF has no way of telling what species are missing from where. In this blog post I review some potential ways GBIF could make global biodiversity hunger maps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding gridded datasets</title>
      <link>/post/finding-gridded-datasets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/finding-gridded-datasets/</guid>
      <description>EBCC Atlas of European Breeding Birds (gridded)Naturalis Biodiversity Center (NL) - Aves (not gridded)Gridded data in GBIFGridded datasets are a known problem at GBIF. Many datasets have equally-spaced points in a regular pattern. These datasets are usually systematic national surveys or data taken from some atlas (“so-called rasterized collection designs”).
In this blog post I will describe how I found gridded dataset in GBIF.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>