<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data gaps on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/data-gaps/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data gaps on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/data-gaps/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Big National Checklists</title>
      <link>/post/big-national-checklists/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/big-national-checklists/</guid>
      <description>link to interactive mapBig 15-300K total namesMedium 5-15K total namesSmall 0-5K total namesHere I plot the total names in checklists published on GBIF linked to a single country. A checklist dataset is a term for any dataset that contains primarily a list of taxonomic names. National species checklists are lists of species recorded from a country usually through some organized effort. GBIF has published a guide on best practices for making national checklist datasets, which advises making national checklists as big as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GBIF checklist datasets and data gaps</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-checklist-datasets-and-data-gaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-checklist-datasets-and-data-gaps/</guid>
      <description>A checklist dataset is a catch-all term describing any dataset that contains primarily a list of taxonomic names. The lines between a checklist dataset and an occurrence dataset can be blurry.
GBIF classifies at least 6 types of datasets as checklists.
National (or regional) lists of species exampleTaxonomic list of species exampleSpecies description exampleChecklists made up of other checklists GBIF backbone taxonomy &amp;amp; Catalogue of LifeChecklists with occurrences exampleChecklists made from occurrences exampleThe top two are probably what most people imagine when they think of a checklist dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunger mapping</title>
      <link>/post/hunger-mapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hunger-mapping/</guid>
      <description>Where are we missing biodiversity data?A hunger map is a map of missing biodiversity data (a biodiversity data gap). The main challenge with hunger mapping is proving that a species does not exist but should exist in a region. Hunger maps are important because they could be used to prioritize funding and digitization efforts. Currently, GBIF has no way of telling what species are missing from where. In this blog post I review some potential ways GBIF could make global biodiversity hunger maps.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>