<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GBIF on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/gbif/</link>
    <description>Recent content in GBIF on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/gbif/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequenced-based data on GBIF - What you need to know before analyzing data</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-molecular-data-quality/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-molecular-data-quality/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned in my previous post, a lot more sequence-based data has been made available on GBIF this past year. MGnify alone, published 295 datasets for a total of 13,285,109 occurrences. Even though most of these occurrences are Bacteria or Chromista, more than a million of them are animals and more than 300,000 are plants. So chances are, that even if you are not interested in bacteria, you might encounter sequence-based data on GBIF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequence-based data on GBIF - Sharing your data</title>
      <link>/post/gbif-molecular-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/gbif-molecular-data/</guid>
      <description>GBIF is trying to make it easier to share sequence-based data. In fact, this past year alone, we worked with UNITE to integrate species hypothesis for fungi and with EMBL-EBI to publish 295 metagenomics datasets.
Unfortunately, documentation is not as quick to follow. Although we have now an FAQ on the topic, I thought that anyone could use a blog post with some advice and examples.
Note that this blog post is not intended to be documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>