<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>occurrence on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/tags/occurrence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in occurrence on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://data-blog.gbif.org/tags/occurrence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Identifying potentially related records - How does the GBIF data-clustering feature work?</title>
      <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/clustering-occurrences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/clustering-occurrences/</guid>
      <description>Many data users may suspect they’ve discovered duplicated records in the GBIF index. You download data from GBIF, analyze them and realize that some records have the same date, scientific name, catalogue number and location but come from two different publishers or have slightly different attributes.
There are many valid reasons why these duplicates appear on GBIF. Sometimes an observation was recorded in two different systems, sometimes several records correspond to herbaria duplicates (you can check the work of Nicky Nicolson on the topic), sometimes a specimen was digitized twice, sometimes a record has been enriched with genetic information and republished via a different platform&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the flags &#34;Collection match fuzzy&#34;, &#34;Collection match none&#34;, &#34;Institution match fuzzy&#34;, &#34;Institution match none&#34; and how to remove them?</title>
      <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/grscicoll-flags/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/grscicoll-flags/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You are a data publisher of occurrence data through GBIF.org, care about your data quality, and wonder what to do about the issue flags that show up on your occurrences. You might have noticed a new type flag this year relating to collection and institution codes and identifiers. They are the result of our attempt at linking specimens records to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gbif.org/grscicoll&#34;&gt;our Registry of Scientific Collections (GRSciColl)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to choose a dataset class on GBIF?</title>
      <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/choose-dataset-type/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/choose-dataset-type/</guid>
      <description>If you are a (first time) publisher on GBIF and you are trying to decide which type of dataset would best fit your data, this blogpost is for you.
All the records shared on GBIF are organized into datasets. Each dataset is associated with some metadata describing its content (the classic &amp;ldquo;what, where, when, why, how&amp;rdquo;). The dataset&amp;rsquo;s content depends strongly on the dataset&amp;rsquo;s class. GBIF currently support four types of dataset:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
