<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GRSciColl on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/categories/grscicoll/</link>
    <description>Recent content in GRSciColl on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://data-blog.gbif.org/categories/grscicoll/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Making collection content discoverable when you don’t have occurrences published on GBIF</title>
      <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/grscicoll-collection-descriptors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/grscicoll-collection-descriptors/</guid>
      <description>This blog post is a tutorial on how to upload collection descriptors in the Global Registry of Scientific Collections (GRSciColl).
If you are someone working with a physical collection or work with people who do, you might be interested in making these collections findable. Ideally, the content of these collections would be digitized and made available online on relevant platforms like GBIF.org, iDigBio.org, ALA.org.au, etc. Sharing digital specimen records is a great way to ensure the discoverability of collection content.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Global Registry of Scientific Collections (GRSciColl) in 2021</title>
      <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/grscicoll-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/grscicoll-2021/</guid>
      <description>The Global Registry of Scientific Collections, also known as GRSciColl, has been available on GBIF.org since 2019 but it recently got some more attention when we connected it to GBIF occurrences. Now is the perfect time to share a bit of GRSciColl history and what we plan for its future.
A brief history of GRSciColl First of all, here are a few facts about GrSciColl today, at the start of 2021:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
