<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Andrew Rodrigues on GBIF Data Blog</title>
    <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/author/andrew-rodrigues/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Andrew Rodrigues on GBIF Data Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://data-blog.gbif.org/author/andrew-rodrigues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Species Occurrence Data and Corporate Sustainability Frameworks</title>
      <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/2025-10-28-species-occurrence-data-and-corporate-sustainability-frameworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/2025-10-28-species-occurrence-data-and-corporate-sustainability-frameworks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As the business and financial sectors increasingly look towards integrating biodiversity within their sustainability frameworks, this overview outlines the different frameworks that exist, the sectors they belong to, and how the &lt;strong&gt;GBIF infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;data it provides&lt;/strong&gt; can support these sectors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing GBIF-mediated occurrence data to conserve EDGE species</title>
      <link>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/accessing-occurrence-data-to-conserve-edge-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://data-blog.gbif.org/post/accessing-occurrence-data-to-conserve-edge-species/</guid>
      <description>Evolutionarily Distinct and Globally Endangered or EDGE species have few close relatives on the tree of life and are often extremely unusual in the way they look, live and behave, as well as in their genetic make-up. They represent a unique and irreplaceable part of the world’s natural heritage.
 After seeing an open call for projects that extend existing protected area networks for the conservation of EDGE species through the EDGE Protected Area and Conserved Area Fund, I wanted to see what data is currently available through GBIF that could help guide decisions on conservation financing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
